Finding Aid for Michigan Association for Media in Education records, 1949-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Association for Media in Education records 1949-1999
Michigan Association for Media in Education.
3 oversize volumes
23 linear feet
87244 Bz 2; BZ Outsize
Records largely of predecessor organizations, the Michigan Association of School Librarians and the Michigan Audio-Visual Association; includes photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was received in several accessions. Records of the Michigan Association of School Librarians were donated by Theodosia Conklin, Historian, on April 6, 1972. (Donor no. 4599 ) Records of the Michigan Audio-Visual Association were donated by Maxine L. Hough, Executive Secretary, on August 23, 1974; a third major accession came from the organization in 2009.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Michigan Association for Media in Education (MAME) came into being on January 1, 1974, when two earlier organizations merged for the potential power and influence of greater numbers. The two predecessors, the Michigan Association of School Librarians (MASL) and the Michigan Audio-Visual Association (MAVA) built on such traditions as joint conferences, newsletters, and committees in establishing the new organization.
Mrs. Lois T. Place, Director of School Libraries of the Detroit Public Schools, was the guiding spirit behind MASL, organizing a small group of librarians who met in November of 1949. Additional planning meetings, with growing numbers of participants, were held in the spring of 1950, and the first meeting of the Steering Committee occurred on July 12 of that year. The constitution of the new organization, with a charter membership of sixty-five, was ratified at the November 3-4, 1950 Charter Meeting, held at Haven Hill Lodge in Milford, Michigan. In addition to providing school librarians with an opportunity to share problems and ideas, the new organization was aimed at promoting better understanding among school librarians, administrators, teachers and students.
According to its constitution, dated December 1, 1950, the Michigan Audio-Visual Association, with a charter membership of forty, was established to "advance education through the more efficient selection, utilization, evaluation, and administration of the audio-visual materials of instruction."
A Merger Exploration Committee sent a study questionnaire to MASL and MAVA members in early 1972, and reported favorable results at the Spring Combined Conference. A Constitutional Revision Committee was appointed shortly thereafter, and overwhelming approval of the results of their efforts was announced at the 1973 Combined Conference. On December 31, 1973, both MASL and MAVA ceased to exist. On January 1, 1974, MAME, a new educational media organization with a membership soon to surpass 1,000, was born.
The record group is divided into four series: Michigan Association of School Librarians (MASL); Michigan Audio-Visual Association (MASL); MASL-MAVA combined activities; and Michigan Association for Media in Education.
Subjects:
Authors, American--Michigan.; Libraries--Michigan.; Michigan Association for Media in Education.; Michigan Association of School Librarians.; Michigan Audio-Visual Association.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Michigan Association for Media in Education.; Michigan Association of School Librarians.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Michigan Association of School Librarians
  The bulk of the record group is comprised of the records of the Michigan Association of School Librarians. In the original order imposed by the organization, records are arranged by school year and thereafter by administrative function or document type. Sample file designations include Board of Directors, Board Meetings, Conferences, Publicity, Correspondence, Regions and Supervisors, SLAAM (Student Library Assistant Association of Michigan), Annual Reports, and History. Although there is slight variation from year to year, and clear evidence of the organization's growth in both size and complexity, file organization remains essentially the same. A file organization chart provided by MASL is included in the file "MASL: Miscellaneous 1973-1974" in Box 3. Material types in administrative function files include calendars of events, membership lists, meeting agendas and minutes, treasurer's reports, conference programs and planning information, and committee reports. A set of MASL newsletters is also included, as are three scrapbooks which further document the organization's history. Although the scrapbooks duplicate some materials in the files, they also provide a more personal look at the organization through informal photographs, souvenir items such as name tags and autographed programs, newsclippings, and annotations. Files and scrapbooks combine to form a comprehensive picture of MASL's history.
  - Records 1949-1973 (Box 1)
    - 1949-Spring 1962, 12 volumes (Box 1)
    - Fall 1962-Spring 1970, 9 volumes (Box 2)
    - Records Fall 1970-1973, 4 volumes (Box 3)
  - Newsletters, Volume I, Number 1-Volume XI, Number 1 1956-Fall 1971 (Box 3)
    (also include May 12, 1951 News Bulletin)
  - Forward [journal] Official File, November 1951-Fall 1973) (Box 3)
    - Volume I, Number 1-Volume XVIII, Number 3 November 1951-Spring 1969 (Box 3)
    - Volume XIX, Number 1-Volume XX, Number 2 Fall 1969-Spring 1971 (Box 3)
    - Volume XXI, Number 1-Volume XXXI, Number 1 Fall 1971-Fall 1973 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous 1973-1974 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook #1 1950-1960 (Volume 1)
  - Scrapbook #2 1960-Spring 1968 (Volume 2)
  - Scrapbook #3 1968-1973 (Volume 3)
- Michigan Audio-Visual Association
  Michigan Audio-Visual Association records, identified as "History" in the file designations, are very similar to those of MASL, both in material types and organization. Again, original order has been retained.
  - Constitution December 1, 1950; Charter Members, 1950-1951 Officers (Box 3)
  - History 1950-Spring 1963 (Box 3)
  - History Fall 1963-1973, 9 volumes (Box 4)
  - Newsletters 1963-1972 (Box 4)
- MASL-MAVA
  The MASL-MAVA series concerns the 1973 Combined Conference and the Constitutional Committee.
  - Combined Conference Reports 1973 (Box 4)
  - Constitutional Committee 1972-1973 (Box 4)
- Michigan Association for Media in Education
  The Michigan Association for Media in Education material, the bulk of which was received in 2009, includes two principal sub-series: History and Conferences. Each of these is comprised of binders arranged by year. The History volumes include constitution and articles of incorporation; membership materials; board of directors minutes and financial material; records of organization officers, divisions, standing committees, and affiliates; and newsletters and various subject files. Each of the binders contains a detailed index. The Conference volumes relate to the yearly meeting of the organization and include agendas, programs, evaluations and related material. Other MAME materials include scrapbooks, publication of the organization, and miscellaneous sound cassettes and photographic slides.
  - Michigan Newsletter, March and June 1974 (Box 4)
  - History
    (in yearly binders)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 5)
    - 1976-1978 (Box 6)
    - 1979-1981 (Box 7)
    - 1982-1984 (Box 8)
    - 1985-1987 (Box 9)
    - 1988-1990 (Box 10)
    - 1991-1993 (Box 11)
    - 1994-1996 (Box 12)
    - 1997-1999 (Box 13)
  - Conferences
    - 1974-1977 (Box 14)
    - 1978-1980 (Box 15)
    - 1981-1984 (Box 16)
    - 1985-1988 (Box 17)
    - 1989-1991 (Box 18)
    - 1992-1994 (Box 19)
    - 1995-1997 (Box 20)
    - 1998-1999 (Box 21)
  - Financial
    - 1974-1976 (Box 22)
  - Scrapbooks
    (include clippings, program announcements photographs, etc.)
    - Region 9, Saginaw County (Box 23)
      - 1975-1979 (Box 23)
      - 1980-1992 (Box 23)
    - Region II 1974-late 1980s (Box 23)
  - Publications
    - Before and After the Censor: a resource manual on intellectual freedom Fall 1987 (Box 23)
    - Selection Policies: a guide to updating and writing (Intellectual Freedom Committee; 1978 ) (Box 23)
    - Who's Where in Books (Michigan Association of School Librarians) (Box 23)
    - Bicentennial Broadside; an annotated bibliography & resource guide ( 1975 ) (Box 23)
    - Recommended materials for a professional library in the school ( 1962 ) (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous sound cassettes, filmstrips, and photographic slides (Box 23)
Related Material
Issues of the organization’s newsletter Media Spectrum, 1974-2009, have been separately cataloged.